Finding Aid for Clara Marian Wheeler papers, 1874-1948
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Clara Marian Wheeler papers
1874-1948
Wheeler, Clara Marian, 1861-1946.
86277 Aa 2; UAm
Grand Rapids, Michigan educator, principal of the Grand Rapids Kindergarten Training School, and advocate of kindergarten education. Correspondence, lecture and class notes, programs, photographs, and miscellaneous scrapbooks, ledgers, and account books.
6 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. C.J. Olsen (donor no. 2252 ) and came to the library in 1946.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Clara Marian Wheeler was born April 25, 1861 in Grand Rapids, Michigan. She was the daughter of Reuben and Marian Wheeler. Wheeler was a teacher and spent more than half a century in kindergarten teaching. She was a charter member of the Grand Rapids Kindergarten association, which established a training school in 1894 and was instrumental in getting Mrs. Lucretia Willard Treat to come here from Chicago to head the school. Clara Wheeler was secretary of the school until 1904, when on Mrs. Treat's retirement she became principal. She remained until the school was discontinued in 1919. For the next five years Wheeler conducted a private kindergarten school in her home. Beginning in 1921 Wheeler joined the Parent-Teacher association, becoming an officer of the state organization, serving as treasurer, secretary and historian. She would be active in this organization until her death in 1946.
The collection is comprised of correspondence and other papers largely concerning kindergarten education and her involvement in a parent and teacher organization. The series in the collection are Biographical / Personal materials, Correspondence; Kindergarten education; National Congress of Parents and Teachers; and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Blow, Susan E. (Susan Elizabeth), 1843-1916.; Child care--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Education--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; First Methodist Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Froebel Study Club of Grand Rapids (Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.); Grand Rapids Kindergarten Training School.; Grand Rapids Public Library (Grand Rapids, Mich.); International Kindergarten Union.; Kent County Sunday School Association (Mich.); Kindergarten.; Methodist Episcopal Church--Michigan--Grand Rapids.MichiganGrand Rapids.; Michigan. Dept. of Public Instruction.; Michigan Kindergarten Association.; Schools--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Teachers--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Women teachers--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; School administrators--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Women school administrators--Michigan--Grand Rapids.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Children.; Costumes.; Education.; Grand Rapids Kindergarten Training School.; International Kindergarten Union.; Junior American Citizens Club.; Kindergartens.; Libraries--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; National Congress of Parents and Teachers.; Reading.; Teachers--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Wheeler, Clara Marian, 1861-1946.; Women--Work.
Contributors:
Fall, Delos, 1848-1921.; Garfield, Charles William, 1848-1934.; Harrison, Elizabeth, 1849-1927.; Keeler, Fred L.; Kelley, Patrick Henry, 1867-1925.; National Association for the Promotion of Kindergarten Education.; National Congress of Parents and Teachers.; National Kindergarten Association.; Treat, Lucretia Willard, 1842-1904.; Wiggin, Kate Douglas Smith, 1856-1923.; Willard, Frances E. (Frances Elizabeth), 1839-1898.; Wright, Luther Lamphere, 1856-1922.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical / Personal materials
  - Obituaries and other biographical information (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, marriages and deaths of friends and associates of Clara Wheeler, 1895-1908 (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids First Methodist Church, 1911-1947; undated (Box 1)
  - Kent County Sunday School Association, 1902-1923; 2 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Undated, 1874-1947; 22 folders (Box 1)
- Kindergarten education
  - Grand Rapids Kindergarten Training School, 1892-1928; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Kindergarten movement, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Grand Rapids Froebel Study Club, 1891-1941; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - International Kindergarten Union programs, 1895-1913 (Box 2)
  - Graduates of the Grand Rapids Kindergarten Training School, 1896-1916; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Notes of lectures of Susan E. Blow, 1905-1913; undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Teacher exams, 1895-1898; undated (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1895-1910; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Printed material, 1889-1917; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Lecture and class notes
    - A (Box 3)
    - B, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - C (Box 3)
    - F, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - G, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - H-K (Box 3)
    - Kindergarten, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - L-N (Box 3)
    - P (Box 3)
    - S, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - T, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - W-Y (Box 3)
    - Froebel gifts nos. 1-2 (Box 3)
    - Froebel gifts nos. 3-4 (Box 3)
    - Froebel gifts nos. 5-6 (Box 4)
    - Froebel gifts nos.7-8 (Box 4)
    - Froebel gifts nos. 9-10 (Box 4)
    - Light Songs, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Trade Plays, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 9 folders (Box 4)
  - Class room demonstrations and examples, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Class room demonstrations and examples, 10 folders (Box 5)
  - Kindergarten programs, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellanea, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellanea, 5 folders (Box 6)
- National Congress of Parents and Teachers
  - Reports and other materials, 1922-1941; 3 folders (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous scrapbooks, journals, and account books (Box 6)
  - Photographs: Portraits; photographs of Wheeler with students of a petting farm and with colleagues at Parent-Teacher Association fiftieth anniversary; and group photographs of the International Kindergarten Union (ca. 1900) and the Junior American Citizens Club (Box 6)
    (see also oversize folder UAm)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Blow, Susan E. (Susan Elizabeth), 1843-1916.
Undated, October 10, 1904, June 30, 1905, Sept. 28, 1907, March 13, 1909, Dec. 30, 1910
Fall, Delos, 1848-1921.
Oct. 23, 1897, 1902-1904
Garfield, Charles William, 1848-1934.
Apr. 20, 1900, May 26, 1920, Apr. 27, 1934
Harrison, Elizabeth, 1849-1927.
Undated, Jan. 17, 1905, Sept. 4, 1905, 1906, Oct. 22, 1907, Aug. 14, 1908, 1914 undated, Sept. 27, 1916, Oct. 29, 1917, June 27, 1919, Apr. 14, 1927
Keeler, Fred L.
1914, 1915, 1917, 1918
Kelley, Patrick Henry, 1867-1925.
1905, 1906
National Association for the Promotion of Kindergarten Education
1910, 1911
National Congress of Parents and Teachers
1925-1927, 1929, 1931
National Kindergarten Association
1913, 1928
Treat, Lucretia Willard, 1842-1904.
Dec. 21, 1897
Wiggin, Kate Douglas Smith, 1856-1923.
Feb. 20, 1891
Willard, Frances E. (Frances Elizabeth), 1839-1898.
Oct. 7, 1890
Wright, Luther Lamphere, 1856-1922.
1907-1909, 1911, 1912